hey guys welcome to concept en coding
this is Shan and today in the third part
of transaction management of spring boot
we are going to cover the isolation
level and this is very very important
topic as part of hld also how do you
maintain a concurrency and as well in
day-to-day life if you working so let's
start without wasting any time so if I
want to Define isolation level in one
line I would say that it tells how the
changes made by one transaction are
visible to other transaction running in
parallel
right if you have confusion with this
line don't worry we are going to see a
lot of examples which
will make clear this
sentence so if you have to use this
isolation how we can use is that when
you are using this annotation at theate
transaction you
can use this like isolation equals to
isolation. read committed there are four
types of isolation read uncommitted read
committed repeatable committed and
serializable so there are four types of
isolation level so which type of
isolation you have to use you can
provide it here let's say if you are not
providing anything here if you're not
providing anything here what would be
the default isolation level so see
default isolation level depend upon the
DB which we are using we can't say that
hey default is always read committed or
repeatable committed no it depend upon
your DB and it might change in future
also okay so let's say all mostly
relational database use read committed
but it is possible that some of the
relational database might use repeatable
committed right so we have to properly
read whichever DB are using if you're
using post or MySQL you have to read
properly that which isolation is the
default isolation it support right why
it is important too much because of
concurrency okay if you are using read
uncommitted it has very high concurrency
means so many request can run in
parallel
if you are using
serializable the concurrency is very low
very low means very less transaction can
run in parallel now you can ask me that
hey sh concurrency high is good right we
want as much transaction can run in
parallel so we should always use r
uncommitted no so see it's always like
if there is an advantage there is a
disadvantage also so we have to
understand understand properly in which
and when we have to use what that is
actually what important is so before I
come to read uncommitted read committed
repeatable committed or Ser serializable
before I come to isolation level let's
first understand this
problems there are three problems which
actually this isolation level resolve
okay so let's first start with what is
is dirty read
prog so what is dirty read problem dirty
read problem says that transaction a
read the uncommitted data of other
transaction okay and if other
transaction get rolled back the
uncommitted data which is read by
transaction a is known as dirty read now
what let's see this definition with an
example so let's say this is the time
this is transaction a this is
transaction B and this is let's say a
current DB
status at time T1 both the transaction
started in parallel begin transaction
begin transaction and this is the
current state of the DB id123 and status
of the column status is currently
free at time
T2 transaction B is updating the row
which has ID 1 2 3 and changing it to
booked so so DB status is currently 1 2
3 and status is booked but at this point
of time transaction B has not
committed right it is still in progress
transaction is still in progress it is
not yet committed or roll back it is
still running okay so this status booked
this change by transaction B but it is
not committed this transaction is not
committed so at time T3 the transaction
a read the row with ID 1 2 3 so in the
dirty
read the transactions also read the
uncommitted data so even this
status which is change by transaction B
is not committed yet still it reads it
so transaction a is able to read what is
the status book okay now at time T4 now
let's say transaction B some issue has
come and does the roll back and now you
know when the roll back happen all the
changes which it has done they again
goes back to the previous state so it
again goes back from to free but the
problem here is transaction here has
read the uncommitted changes booked
which is now not there into the DB this
is known as dirty read transaction a is
is now suffered from a dirty read
problem because it has read a row which
has uncommitted
data right so the transaction which is
not committed all the changes is also
read
by other transaction then it is known as
dirty read
problem okay so if this problem is clear
let's move to another program which is
called non repeatable read
program okay
okay if suppose transaction a reads the
same row several times and there is a
chance that it get different value then
it is known as non repeatable read
program let's understand with an example
what this definition says let's say this
is the transaction a this is the current
DB status at time T1 transaction is
started and this is the current state of
DB id1 status free at time T2 a read
call has been made by transaction a for
the id1 so what is the status is fre
free okay now let's say at time T3 some
other
transaction has happened and changed the
status from free to booked and also
committed the changes so committed
also so at time
T4 if transaction a again runs the same
query read row id1 trying to read the
same row it will not get the same data
it will get data got changed now what is
the status is getting
booked okay so that's where it is called
as non repeatable read read the same row
several times and there is a chance that
you get different
value so this problems is clear like
okay what this problem means that if you
read a row multiple times there is a
chance that whatever the value you were
getting before now it's get changed and
how like this is one kind of a use case
where this value get
changed and the third problem is called
the Phantom read problem the Phantom
read problem says that if suppose
transaction a execute same query several
times but there is a chance that the
rows returns are different itself then
it is known as Phantom read
program let's understand this definition
with an example let's say at time T1 the
transaction a started the transaction
begin transaction and this is the
current state of the DB current status
is id1 is status is free ID row ID3 is
status is booked currently let's say two
rows are there
so at time T2 transaction a is trying to
read a row where ID greater than zero
and ID less than 5 so what all rows will
come ID greater than zero and ID less
than five so this both the rows will
come right so it will read two rows with
ID 1 and
three now let's say at time T3 some
other transaction inserted the row with
id2 and committed also so now let's say
that this new this is the new row has
been added by some other transaction at
time T3 and also
committed okay now at time T4 the
transaction a is running the same query
again okay read row with ID greater than
zero and ID less than 5 now this
time there is a chance that rows returns
are different now three rows are coming
ID 1 2 3 Because all three are
satisfying this condition ID greater
than zero and ID less than five so this
is known as Phantom read problem when
you are getting different rows itself
with the same query let me also tell you
about DB locking because this is also
required so there are two types of DB
locking one is shared
log shared log and another is exclusive
log
so shared locks is also represented by S
exclusive loog is also represented by
sometime
X okay so shared lock is also known as
read
lock and exclusive lock is also known as
right
log so now let's say that I have a DB in
which I have one row called let's say ID
is one and status is free let's say one
is present so what is read lock or
shared lock so now let's say that there
are two transaction transaction one and
transaction
two so let's say that if transaction one
wants to read this ID
1 it can take shared loog right I can
represent the shared log with s take on
id1 it has taken a shared lock on id1 So
currently somebody is taking a shared
lock on this one who transaction
one now let's say that transaction T to
T2 also want to read this
row will it be able to read it yes
because shared log can be as the name
says that can be shared by multiple
transaction but only for the reading
purpose so transaction two also want to
read it it can also put a shared log and
it can read this same row
so what shared log says that more than
one
transaction can put a shared log and you
can read the value that's all you can
only read but you cannot modify anything
you can only
read in other way the exclusive log
let's say you have this id1 and the
status is free transaction one and
transaction two now let's say if
transaction one has to change something
in this row right and it don't want any
other transaction should either read or
either should write then it can go for
exclusive log exclusive log on
id1 so what exclusive log has been taken
by T1 now let's say that if transaction
to want to
read or write on id1 will it be able to
do that no because there is a exclusive
log present exclusive log says that once
the exclusive log is taken by any
transaction no other transaction would
be able to even read or
write so that's where it says
that if a lock is shared lock can
another shared lock be taken yes you can
take and you can read the
value but if I have a shared log can
another exclusive log can be taken no if
any transaction has taken a shared log
let's say transaction one has taken a
shared loog right it has taken a shared
log and if transaction two says that hey
I want exclusive log on T1 can I take it
it will check hey somebody has already
taken shared log you can't take
exclusive log only you can take shared
log you can read it but you cannot write
it till this shared Lo is
present now if a transaction has
exclusive log right if a transaction has
exclusive log let's say T1 can another
transaction take shared lock on it no
when exclusive lock is taken you can't
even read it you can't even write it so
you can't even read it you can't even
write it you can't do exclusive lock
also okay
so by this point of time two types of of
locking and these three problems if it
is
clear then you will clearly
understand what this
isolations actually solves the
problem so read
uncommitted isolation level solves
nothing you will have a dirty read Pro
uh problem you will have non repeatable
problem and you will have panm read
problem also why you can ask right
interviewer can ask why read uncommitted
has all three
problems because the read uncommitted do
not even take read LW do not even apply
the right LW also so now let's say that
if in DB I have an
ID one and the status is free
transaction one and transaction two
transaction
one reads it it do not put any log it
just read it
right and transaction one transaction
two want to write it it can directly go
ahead and change it there is no locking
at all if there is no locking there is
like whichever transaction want they can
change it and the same dirty read
program can come transaction two can
change it to
booked which transaction T1 can read it
and what if transaction to got roll back
the same dirty read can come similarly
the same non- repeatable read and the
Phantom read program whichever we have
discussed above the same thing can come
because no locking has been acquired by
read
uncommitted so the one follow-up
question which comes also right then why
this isolation level exist when all
three programs are present no locks are
required then why do this isolation
level exist itself this isolation level
is only used when you have only read
application
if you have an application where the use
case is only read you have an static
data and you only read then only this
isolation level is useful otherwise it
is of no used like it's very risky to
use this because of all three progs
which can come so it has to be used very
very like if you're properly clear that
these three problems will not impact
your business logic or but you know
right concurrency would be high
concurrency is very high why because
there is no locking no no transaction is
stopping at all if they want it they can
get the data if they want to write they
can write it simply right there is no
wait time for anybody there is no
locking at the DB
R but this is risky the another one is
read committed so these two are pretty
like you can say that mostly used right
depending upon the use cases read
committed and repeatable
read so read
committed solves dirty read POS dirty
read possible no it solves this problem
so this is
solved but it do not
solve uh non repeatable read and it do
not solve the Panem read
problem but only it solve dirty read
problem problem
so what read commited does is it put a
while reading it put a shared
lock right and as soon as it uh read it
it release the lock as soon as that read
is
done and for the right exclusive lock
Acquired and keep till the end of the
transaction now let's say that you have
transaction one transaction
two right
now here the same thing if transaction
one so let's say this is the
ID one and status is
free now transaction one want to read it
ID 1 so what it will do is it will first
take a shared log on
id1 and it will read the value let's say
read the value status free as soon as
it's read it it release the lock so lock
has been
released so earlier take a shared lock
by transaction one as soon as the read
is done shared lock has been
removed
okay now dirty read program it solved
right that uh if it want to write
anything it will take a exclusive log
now let's say transaction one want to
write on this data so what it will do is
it will take exclusive log
by T1 it will take an exclusive log
right on
id1 now let's say it will change the
status
to
booked it will change the status to
booked but now here if you see it will
release
this exclusive log only at the end of
the transaction end of transaction end
of transaction could be either
commit or roll back
only after this only it will release
this lock so now since it has taken this
if now in let's say this is Time 1 time
two at time three now let's say at time
T3 any other transaction wants to read
it will transaction two will be able to
read it no because exclusive log is
there so transac 2 would not be able to
read it so it is safe from
the dirty read program you can't read it
till it is not committed or roll
back
right
but does uh read uncommitted is non is
solving the non-repeatable problem no it
it is not solving it why because let's
say
that here it is running this query now
let's say that it is running this query
transaction
one
read I
id1 and currently what is the status it
got let's say
free this is the DB status for now uh ID
equals to 1 and status
is free this is the DB state for now
table state so at time transaction T1
currently has read it okay so this is at
time
one now at time
two because see during read it just take
a shared lock and after reading it
release the lock also it releases it so
now at time
T2 transaction 2 can uh like take an
exclusive log and update it start begin
the
transaction let's say update the row and
change the ID equals to 1 to
booked okay so at time T2 some other
transaction has taken an exclusive lock
here and changes status from free to
booked okay and also committed also now
the transaction is
completed now at time
three again the transaction one is
running the same query
read id1 what status it will get now
booked right so see the value got
changed so that's
why the read committed do not solves the
non-repeatable read
problem and similarly the Phantom read
problem is also not resolved right the
same thing you can uh change the same to
let's say read query is like a range
query uh read id1 read id1 or you can
say that read
row where ID greater than zero and less
than 5 read all this rows so first time
let's say you get two
rows but since this is only reading so
it will put a shared log which will
ultimately after reading get removed it
will release the
log but at let's say some other time
time T2 some other transaction has
inserted new row let's say some other
transaction insert insert new row the
same like what we see above the Phantom
right insert new row and it begin and
committed the transaction
also right so exclusive log taken and
after committed the transaction to the
lock has been shared lock has been uh
exclusive lock has been removed now at
time T3 the same transaction T1 running
the same query read all rows greater
than Z and less than 5 now this time it
will get earlier it get two rows now
maybe possible that it get this row also
if it follows within the range so now it
might get three rows like what we see
above right
so it do not solve the Panem read
problem also why because while reading
it it just take a shared log but it
release it as soon as
possible okay but during writing it take
an exclusive log and keep it till the
end of the transaction so that's why it
is able to resolve the dirty read but
since the shared log is
released uh some other transaction maybe
after that change something committed
properly end the transaction and during
running the same query it might get the
different data so it do not solve this
to then there is something called
repeatable
read repeatable read solves dirty read
problem solved also solve the non-
repetitive read so these two are solved
but it do not solve this Phantom read
problem how the repeatable read so
during reading it acquir the shared law
and released only at the end of the
transaction not like just after reading
release it no once it taken a share log
on a particular row it will release only
at the end of the transaction similarly
right once the exclusive lock acquired
released only at the end of the
transaction so the same you can try uh
replicating it and understand with the
same two transactions I have transaction
one and transaction two right at time
one let's say if this is the DB
Row one and ID is one and the status is
free at time one it has acquired a
shared log on ID one so shared log has
been taken by transaction one now let's
say begin
transaction now this lock will not be
released until this transaction is not
ended end can be happen through either
commit or it could be roll
back so let's say this is something
whenever like let's say whenever
whatever the time would be some I
whatever the time would be till this
time this lock is now not going to
remove okay
so other transactions can only read
it you can only read it but can any
other let's say in mid here in this time
mid let's say time T2 can this take an
exclusive log and update this one no
because sh when the shared log is taken
you know that you can't update it only
you can read it so you you you will not
get a exclusive log so no matter how
much time you will read the same row I
read again here at time T2 you will get
the same stat here also you got free
here also you got free if later on also
you would do read here also you would
get
free okay so now it's you have resolved
the non repeatable Problem by putting a
shared log and keep it till the end of
the transition no other transition in
now between this time can change
it right and also the dirty read also
resolve because dirty
read dirty read problem it's get
resolved why because the log exclusive
loog now let's say that the same
row transaction one transaction two
now let's say that transaction one wants
to update it it take an exclusive log on
Row one and wants to change it from free
to
booked so this will get to booked but
here exclusive log is taken by
T1 and this log would be kept till the
end of the transaction either committed
properly or roll
back now transaction two in mid cannot
even take shared log for reading or
cannot even take exclusive log for
writing so it cannot even read it so you
dirty read problem is also solved till
this lock is not removed and it will
only get removed once it there is
properly committed or it is rolled back
properly okay but pantom read problem is
not resolved how now here if you see
that if you have two
rows with ID one and let's say four here
you have free here if you have let's say
pending some status this is my DB table
this is ID this is
status okay so now what do happen is
let's say transaction one transaction
two at time
T1 okay let's say you have
read ID greater than zero and ID less
than five so how many rows so you have
put a shared log now shared log
by
T1 okay on which row on here if I put
this shared
log here by T1 shared log here by T1
both the
rows okay so begin transaction so now
this log will be kept till this
transaction is not completed either
commit or roll
back now let's say this is at T1 and now
let's say at time
T2 another
transaction started the begin
transaction and take an exclusive log or
you can say that doing a
insert with ID equals to 2 so see 1 14
id2 is not there so some other row has
inserted a new
row two with ID new row is
inserted two and some other status let's
say
free because see there is no shared lock
on this right two part so any other
transaction can go ahead and insert it
and complete this transaction let's say
properly
committed okay now let's say at time
three this transaction T1 runs the same
query again again read ID greater than Z
and ID less than
5 will it get the same two rows earlier
like it get 1 and four now it will get 1
4 and
two because this query is now satisfying
this three so Phantom read problem is
there still there in this repeatable
read the last one is serializable what
what serializable does is it there is no
dirty read problem here there is no
non-reputable problem here and there is
no Fantom read it resolved all
solved solved
solved
how the serializable same as repeatable
log read log strategy so it it uses the
same strategy during
reading it requ it take a shared lock
and release only only at the end of the
transaction exclusive log is taken while
writing and released only at the end of
the transaction it does the same thing
but it apply the range
lock it apply the range lock now here if
you
see the Phantom read program I will tell
you the same let's say this we will pick
the same thing the two
Row 1 and four status is free some
status is
pending now in the if you are if you are
using the
serialization uh isolation level if
transaction one and transaction two are
running transaction two let's say begin
the
transaction and it is doing this at time
one
read ID greater than zero and ID less
than 5
so what it will
do it will so read it is doing reading
so means it will put a shared log and it
will release only at the end of the
transaction correct that's what it is
does like repeatable read but one
changes it put a range lock range lock
means all the 0 to 1 2 3 4 so it will
put a shared log here by T1 shared log
here at time T2 uh not T2 T1 uh
transaction T1 put a Shar log on this
also it put a range log so this is kind
of a range
log range log means now 1 2 3 4 these
all are kind of log now let's say at
time two some other transaction has
started begin
transaction now wants to take an
exclusive log and in
insert a with ID equals to 2 will it be
able to insert it no this will not be
because at second row also range log is
already present here which is a shared
log which no other transaction can
insert it in the
mid between this one and uh ID greater
than zero and five whatever the rows are
satisfying this
condition a share PA log would be
put right and it's a range log means
anything coming in mid of it also it
will get
log that's how it is solving the Phantom
read problem because now no other
transaction would be able to insert any
new data in mid and so that now at time
T3 if the same query runs again read ID
greater than zero and ID less than 5 the
same two rows will get return so there
is no new rows will come because another
transaction won't be able to insert
because range log has been present all
all this all this rows which are
satisfying this plus any rows which are
coming in mid those are get loged you
cannot do any insertion in
mid but this one thing clarifies you
that the concurrency of serializable is
very less or very low
the concurrency
Rises but the risk of certain problems
arises like
this so during which DB to use and which
isolation level to use during
transaction it is very important
decision interviewer might this is very
interesting topic for an interviewer
that you know which isolation level
should use so
generally depending upon the requirement
either repe reable read or
repeatable uh read committed or
repeatable committed out of this two
only this is one is required because
they give like some yes concurrency is
there but also problem is solved so
whenever this question come ask
interviewer that okay whatever the
application we are building non
repeatable read is a problem or not if
non- repeatable read is not a progam
right go for read committed
if it is a problem go for repeatable
commit
right so I hope this is uh clear to you
but this uh if let's say that if you ask
me right here sh like where this shared
loog exclusive loog actually code is
present see here in your application you
will simply write
read let's say uh select query you will
write select query right select asress
from your
table where ID equals to 1 you will
write only this query now depending upon
the isolation level which your DB is
using there is uh something called DB
transaction
manager right with each DB there is some
transaction manager so this locking code
okay I am using isolation level I have
to use isolation level read so during
application you just tell which
isolation level to
use hey use
read
committed then it will during select
query it will make sure that it will put
a shared lock and release it as soon as
you read it so this taking a lock
releasing the lock taking a shared lock
releasing the lock is exist into DB
transaction manager which is not uh like
at at a application layer this is not uh
visible to us it's
abstracted okay we just simply write
insert query update query but only
isolation level is something which will
tell to the DB transaction manager which
ultimately talks to the
DB but what locking it should use when
to use when to release this is Guided by
isolation level and that's where the if
you read the definition
again it tells how how the changes made
by one transaction are visible to
another transaction running in parallel
I hope this definition makes sense
now with that being said like the
transaction management is a spring board
I'm completed and see you soon with the
next topic of the springboard bye